Well, all right. At long last, it's time
to talk about US military operations
during World War II and America's role
in the post-war peace. So, if you're
ready to get them brain cows milked,
let's get to it. So, the first thing you
need to know is that if you were to
surgically open the general American
consciousness during World War II, you
would have found a very specific purpose
for their willingness to fight. And that
purpose, at least in the American mind,
was altogether righteous, namely to keep
the world safe for freedom and democracy
against the hostile forces of fascism
and militaristic authoritarianism. And
this righteous urge was perhaps most
famously articulated by Franklin
Roosevelt in what became known as his
four freedoms speech which he delivered
almost a year before Japan's attack on
Pearl Harbor. But it ultimately became
the ideological foundation for American
involvement in the war. So in the speech
Roosevelt declared that all people in
the world ought to know freedom of
speech, freedom of worship, freedom from
want and freedom from fear. And more to
the point, the only way the global
community could enjoy these freedoms
would be if democracy flourished
worldwide without the threat of
aggressive authoritarian government. And
so while Roosevelt used this speech to
reassert US neutrality, the bombing of
Pearl Harbor meant that Americans
themselves would go to war to protect
those freedoms. Now this kind of
ideological patriotism indeed sustained
much of the war effort, but the ideas
became reality when the war was over and
the full breadth of Japanese and German
atrocities came to light. In the
Pacific, the Japanese captured more than
50,000 American prisoners of war and
used them as an enslaved labor force.
For example, they were put to work
building a railroad from Burma to
Thailand. and the harsh conditions the
Japanese imposed on their prisoners led
to thousands of deaths and even more
instances of sickness and malnutrition.
But by far the most expansive and
vicious wartime atrocity came in the
form of the Holocaust carried out by
Nazi Germany. So a key ingredient in
Hitler's extreme form of nationalism was
a desire for a purified race of Germans
and therefore he used his power to
exterminate all those whom he believed
tarnished that racial purity. The
program was known as the final solution.
And though it targeted the Roma and
homosexuals and disabled people and
political enemies, by far its most
sinister target was the Jewish
population. So Hitler made use of
industrial technologies to construct
concentration camps where Jews were sent
for hard labor and also to construct
extermination camps where they were sent
to be mass murdered with industrial
precision and efficiency. Now the
largest of these camps was at Avitz and
at its height 12,000 people were killed
every day by means of large-scale gas
chambers. And in the end about 6 million
Jews were put to death in this way and
about 5 million people that belong to
other targeted groups. And so once these
atrocities came to light, Americans
certainly felt justified that their
cause for fighting was indeed righteous.
Okay. But now we need to consider
exactly how the Allied powers with a
heaping pile of US contribution
ultimately won the war. And there are
four major factors you're going to need
to know. First, it was generally agreed
upon among the allies that without the
enormous industrial output of the United
States, they could not have won the war.
In fact, during the Tehran conference,
it was reported that Joseph Stalin of
all people raised his glass and toasted
to American industry as the reason for
the eventual Allied victory. And since I
flapp my mouth hole at length about that
in the previous video, we'll just leave
it there. Okay. The second reason the US
contributed to the Allied victory was
because of technological and scientific
advances. And I'll give you two
examples. First, a black American
surgeon named Charles Drew made
significant advancements in blood
transfusion procedures. In particular,
Drew improved techniques for storing
blood at a large scale and in doing so
facilitated the success of large blood
banks which military medics used to save
the lives of thousands of Allied
soldiers who otherwise would have died
from their wounds. And then second,
let's consider aerial bombing
technology. Now, although aerial combat
was definitely present in World War I,
it was significantly improved during
World War II and became a main feature
of military campaigns. And to further
improve the accuracy of bombing
campaigns, the US developed a technology
called Nordon bomb site, which used
rudimentary computers on planes to
accurately calculate the trajectory of
bombs. And as the US increasingly relied
on bombing campaigns to disable enemy
industrial infrastructure, the Nordan
bomb site technology made such campaigns
all the more effective. And then the
third reason the US contributed to the
Allied victory was a handful of highly
strategic military campaigns. And there
are two you're going to need to
remember. First, in the European theater
of war, you're going to need to know
about the D-Day campaign. So by the time
the US joined the war, the Soviet Union
was absorbing the brunt of German
aggression in Eastern Europe. And so
Stalin was getting real impatient for
his British and American allies to open
a western front against Germany to
relieve some of that pressure. And so
after stalling for several years in
1944, the Allies launched the D-Day
invasion, also known as Operation
Overlord into Nazi occupied France. And
on that day, a combination of American,
British, and Canadian troops crossed the
English Channel and landed on France's
Normandy beaches. And this operation
became the largest and most
technologically sophisticated amphibious
assault in military history. And despite
sustaining heavy casualties from German
fortifications, the Allied troops
succeeded in establishing a beach head
and from there were able to launch
further inland toward Germany. And that
victory ended up being the first step in
the final defeat of the Germans. And
then over in the Pacific theater, you're
going to need to know about the American
island hopping campaign. Now, since the
Japanese were notoriously stubborn about
surrendering and often fought till the
last of them were dead, General Douglas
MacArthur led US troops to capture
lightly fortified Japanese islands while
skipping the well-defended islands
entirely. And in that way, they were
able to more quickly establish bases
from which to launch a final assault on
the Japanese mainland. And finally, the
fourth major US contribution to the
Allied victory was the dropping of two
atomic bombs on Japan. Now, remember
what I just said, namely that the island
hopping campaign put Americans in a real
good spot to invade the Japanese
mainland. Well, as it turned out, no
Pacific commander really wanted to carry
out such an invasion because by their
reckoning, it would have led to massive
American casualties. But at the end of
the war, the US had a new weapon at its
disposal that would make such an
invasion unnecessary. So since 1942,
Roosevelt had approved and funded a
scientist named J. Robert Oppenheimer to
develop an atomic bomb through the
Manhattan Project. Now, by the time the
bomb was developed and tested and ready,
Roosevelt had died and his vice
president, Harry Truman had to make the
call whether to drop the bomb. And so
when Japan refused Truman's terms for
absolute surrender, he authorized that
two atomic bombs be dropped. One on
Hiroshima and the second on Nagasaki.
And together, these bombs unleashed a
destructive power never before seen in
the history of warfare. And its effects
were devastating. Nearly 200,000
Japanese civilians were instantly killed
in the blasts, and thousands more died
slowly of radiation poisoning. But
regardless, Japan surrendered, and soon
thereafter, the war had finally come to
an end. However, the bombings of
Hiroshima and Nagasaki led to fierce
debates over the morality of using such
powerful weapons. On one hand, President
Truman and his supporters argued that by
using the atomic bombs, the lives of
countless American soldiers were saved
since they were spared a ground
invasion. On the other hand, critics
argued that Hiroshima and Nagasaki were
not strictly military targets and they
were filled with civilians. Okay, now
before we get to all the post-war peace
settlements, I need to tell you about
one other feature of American
involvement in World War II. So, women
and minorities in addition to serving
the war effort on the home front also
made vital contributions to the war by
serving in the military. And in many
cases, this had the effect of improving
their socio-economic status. In terms of
women, a great example here is the code
girls. You see, the US military
recruited about 10,000 STEM educated
women to work as cryptographers who
worked to break secret German and
Japanese codes. And not only did they
decode intelligence that led to the
sinking of many Japanese supply ships,
they also successfully provided false
information to the Germans about the
landing location for the D-Day
operation. And while many of these women
were pressured to return to clerical
jobs or domestic work once the men
returned home from war, their work laid
a strong foundation for future women's
equality movements by providing
undeniable proof that women were every
bit as capable of men to work in
highstakes, highly analytical jobs. And
then in terms of minorities in service,
the Tuskegee Airmen were a shining
example. And as I mentioned in the last
video, this was an all black air combat
unit that trained at the Tuskegee
Institute in Alabama. And despite their
segregated role, this unit fought with
distinction, destroying hundreds of
enemies both in the air and on the
ground. Additionally, Japanese Americans
and indigenous Americans contributed
with distinction as well. All of which
had the effect of changing the widely
held stereotypes that hindered these
groups from enjoying the fullness of
their guaranteed civil liberties. Okay.
And finally, now that the Allies had won
the war, let's consider the largest role
that the United States played in the
contours of the post-war peace. And I'll
just mention three developments. First
of all, the US pushed for expanded
democracy in Europe after the war. And
this plan was largely discussed and
developed in a series of meetings
between what was known as the big three,
namely the United States, Great Britain,
and the Soviet Union. So before the war
ended, the big three met at the Yaltta
conference and they decided on a few
things like how Germany was going to be
jointly occupied by the Soviets and the
Americans and the British and the
French. And additionally, they agreed
that Eastern European nations would have
the ability to choose their leaders
through free elections. And then just
after the war was over, they met at the
Potum Conference where they again
confirmed the plans for the partition of
postwar Germany. But significant
mistrust grew between Truman and Stalin
over democratic elections in Eastern
European states and Truman's deployment
of the atomic bomb since he had kept it
a secret from the Soviets. And by this
point, it was becoming clear that Stalin
intended to claim those Eastern European
nations for himself to act as a buffer
zone against any future German
aggression. And that's going to lead us
right into unit 8 and the Cold War.
Okay. Second, the US shaped the postwar
world through significant financial
investment. So, with the exception of
the damage done in Hawaii to the Pearl
Harbor naval base, the United States
suffered no war damage in the homeland.
But the devastation in Europe and Asia
was profound. And what that meant was
that the US emerged from the war with
its territory and industrial
infrastructure intact while other
nations were just beginning the long and
expensive process of rebuilding all that
was destroyed. And so in that way, the
US led the international rebuilding
effort through various programs like the
Marshall Plan, which we'll discuss more
in the next unit. However, in helping
finance the reconstruction of these war
ravaged nations, the United States was
essentially exporting Roosevelt's
principle of freedom from want. And in
doing so, American policymakers were
able to shape the world order largely as
they wished. And that gave Americans no
small amount of global power. And
finally, third, the US shaped the
post-war world through its role in the
creation of the United Nations. And this
would be the International Peacekeeping
Organization that replaced the largely
ineffective League of Nations. And
because the US held one of five
permanent seats at the head of that
council, a position that came with
absolute veto power, American policy
makers were able to influence global
policy in a way that benefited their own
interests. Okay, if you're studying for
a test, then you can click here to grab
my A Push himler review guide, which is
the fastest way to study. Or you can
click here to watch my other topic
videos for unit 7. I'm glad you came
around. And I'll catch you on the
flip-flop in unit 8.